Grace Hoadley Dodge Papers, 1882-1995 (bulk 1882-1915)
Sophia Smith Collection
Grace Hoadley Dodge papers
1882-1995
1882-1915
Dodge, Grace H. (Grace Hoadley), 1856-1914
MS 603
3 Boxes (1.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Social welfare worker, Philanthropist, Educator. Papers are primarily related to her professional and public life and primarily include biographical writings about Grace Dodge and clipping scrapbooks containing articles by Grace Dodge and about her activities and concerns (1882-1914). The scrapbooks focus on Dodge's efforts on behalf of "working girls" in late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century urban areas.
Grace Hoadley Dodge was born on May 21, 1856 in New York City into a wealthy family with a strong tradition of philanthropic and evangelical activity. She was the oldest of six children born to Sarah Hoadley and William Earl Dodge, Jr. Dodge received most of her education at home from private tutors, but spent two years at Miss Sarah Porter's School in Connecticut (1872-74).
On her return to New York City, she began teaching Sunday School at the Madison Square Chapel and later in industrial schools for the Children's Aid Society. Dodge's interactions with the evangelist Dwight L. Moody, who stayed with the Dodges during his 1876 campaign in New York City, had a profound effect on Grace's decision to dedicate her life to social service work. Her approach was committed and businesslike. She came to regard her work for a wide variety of causes and organizations as full-time employment, with a salary that had been "paid in advance" through her family's business successes.
Drawn to ventures that allowed for close personal association, Dodge often acted as a facilitator, but not a leader of informal clubs. In 1881 she formed a club with factory girls around her own age. Their weekly meetings for "fellowship and discussion" gradually came to include a headquarters, library, recreation rooms, and classes. Within a decade, the concept grew into a national Association of Working Girls' Societies. Her mantra was always to work with, rather than for, working women. Some of the friendships formed in this first club lasted throughout Dodge's life.
Dodge also worked to promote vocational education and practical training as a means of combating poverty. She founded the Kitchen Garden Association in 1880 which was reorganized into the Industrial Education Association in 1884. These groups offered classes in "household arts," manual training, and later, teacher training. The Industrial Education Association was eventually reorganized into Teachers College in 1889 with Dodge as its first Treasurer.
Dodge developed somewhat of a specialty of encouraging organizations with similar missions to join forces in order to increase their effectiveness. In 1906 she brought together two warring national associations of YWCAs to form a single national association. Grace Dodge served as the new Association's first president until her death.
Other organizations benefiting from these talents included the New York Travelers Aid Society, formed in 1907, and the American Social Hygiene Association in 1912.
Grace Dodge died suddenly in her home on December 27, 1914.
The Grace Hoadley Dodge Papers consist of 1.25 linear ft. and are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1882 to 1915. Types of materials include biographical materials, a small amount of correspondence, photographs, newspaper articles, writings, and memorabilia.
Two types of material make up the bulk of the papers: biographical writings about Grace Dodge (1910-80), and clippings scrapbooks containing articles by Grace Dodge and about her activities and concerns (1882-1914). The biographical writings include many memorial tributes from 1915; Abbie Graham's 1926 biography, Grace H. Dodge: Merchant of Dreams; and Ester Katz' 1980 Ph.D. thesis, "Grace Hoadley Dodge: Women and the Emerging Metropolis, 1856-1914." In addition to these there are general biographical materials and memorabilia, small files on three organizations Dodge was involved with (Irene Club, Three P's Circle, and YWCA), photographs of Dodge, and a few of her other writings. The clippings scrapbooks focus on Dodge's efforts on behalf of "working girls" in late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century urban areas. They include articles from a wide variety of newspapers and other periodicals.
This collection is organized into three series:
SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS, MEMORABILIA, AND PHOTOGRAPHS
SERIES II. ORGANIZATIONS
SERIES III. WRITINGS
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The Grace Hoadley Dodge Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records in 2002. They were a gift to the YWCA from Mrs. Cleveland Dodge in 1978.
Manual training--United States--History; Moral education--United States--History; New York (N.Y.)--Civic improvement--History--Sources; Philanthropists--United States--History--Sources; Occupational training for women--United States--History--Sources; Women domestics--United States--History--Sources; Women--Employment--History--Sources; Women in charitable work--United States--History--Sources; Women philanthropists--United States--Biography--Sources; Working class women--United States--History--Sources; Working-women's clubs--United States--History--Sources; Dodge, Grace H. (Grace Hoadley), 1856-1914; Kitchen-Garden Association--History; New York Association of Working Girls Societies--History; Teachers College (New York, NY)--History; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.-History
Related materials can be found in the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
Additional papers of Grace H. Dodge are housed in Special Collections in the Teachers College Library at Columbia University.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS, MEMORABILIA, AND PHOTOGRAPHS
  - General 1910-95, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Association Monthly memorial issues Mar 1915, May 1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Thesis: "Grace Hoadley Dodge: Women and the Emerging Metropolis, 1856-1914" by Esther Katz, New York University 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Grace H. Dodge: A Woman of Creative Faith, reprint of the Mar 1915 memorial issue of the Association Monthly 1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Grace H. Dodge: Merchant of Dreams by Abbie Graham 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Christmas cards 1914-15, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Death
    - General 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memorial services 1914-15 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Condolences and resolutions 1914-15 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Family 1913-92, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia 1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs 1890, 1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- SERIES II. ORGANIZATIONS
  - Irene Club 1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Three P's Circle 1910-14, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - YWCA: annual letters to Club Girls' Council 1908-14 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - General 1885-1911, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - A Bundle of Letters to Busy Girls on Practical Matters 1887 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photocopy of selected articles by Grace Dodge in the 1882-1901 scrapbook in box 3 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbooks of clippings (mostly articles by Grace Dodge) 1882-1901, 1905-14 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS: memorial tributes 1914 (Box 3, Folder 3)